A Guide to the Blacksburg Music Club Records, 1907-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Blacksburg Music Club Records, 1907-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1979-008
2.5 cu. ft. 5 boxes
Records--including correspondence, minutes, programs, financial records, scrapbooks, rosters, and bylaws--of the Blacksburg Music Club, an organization founded to promote the study of music among its members and to stimulate local interest through regularly scheduled musical programs. Also includes materials from the Virginia Federation of Music Clubs and the National Federation of Music Clubs.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Blacksburg Music Club Records were donated to Special Collections in 1979.
Historical Note
A musical appreciation club had been founded in Blacksburg, Virginia as early as 1904. That club was succeeded by the Music and Dramatic Club, founded in 1912 and disbanded around 1928. The Blacksburg Music Club was organized on October 24, 1931, with a goal "to promote the study of musical art among its members and to stimulate the interest in and appreciation of good music in the community." The club soon thereafter became affiliated with the Virginia Federation of Music Clubs and the National Federation of Music Clubs. Club meetings were held monthly from September through May, and programs were staged at various sites in the Blacksburg area and on the campus of Virginia Tech. The club worked closely with other local organizations, including the Blacksburg Concert Association, the Blacksburg Recorder Group, the VPI Glee Club, and the VPI Orchestra, and supported musical programs in local schools by donating money for two pianos, providing funds for special events, and donating the time of members for musical instruction. Perhaps the club's biggest accomplishment was the staging of two Gilbert and Sullivan operettas, The Mikado and Pirates of Penzance in 1958 and 1959, respectively. Due to an aging membership and decline in interest, the Blacksburg Music Club disbanded in 1971.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains records of the Blacksburg Music Club, an organization founded to promote the study of music among its members and to stimulate local interest through regularly scheduled musical programs. The collection includes such materials as correspondence, minutes, programs, newsletters, reports, financial records, membership rosters, constitutions and bylaws, scrapbooks, and printed materials. Also included are materials issued by the Virginia Federation of Music Clubs and the National Federation of Music Clubs, including communications, convention programs, and printed materials.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following three series, based on organizational hierarchy:
Series I. Blacksburg Virginia Music Club, 1907-1971. This series contains materials issued by or directly relating to the local club. Included are administrative correspondence, minutes, programs, newsletters and other communications, annual reports, financial records, club history and bylaws, membership rosters, yearbooks, scrapbooks, and printed material. Also included here is a single folder of materials issued by other southwestern Virginia organizations including the Blacksburg Recorder Society, the Blue Ridge Chamber Music Players, and the Pulaski Music Club.
Series II. Virginia Federation of Music Clubs, 1933-1971. Included in this series are materials relating to the state organization. A folder of materials from the federation's first district, to which the Blacksburg club belonged, consists largely of programs from annual conventions. The remainder of the series contains communications to local clubs and convention programs, as well as administrative and promotional materials
Series III. National Federation of Music Clubs, 1944-1971. This series includes materials received from the local club by the national organization. The series contains reports, circular letters, announcements and other communications; price lists for instructional materials sold by the federation; and printed materials consisting of promotional, instructional, and administrative materials.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following item was removed from the collection and cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
Andrews, Mary Raymond Shipman. The Counsel Assigned. New York: Scribner's, [1940?].
Index Terms
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.)
Contents List
- Series I. Blacksburg Music Club, 1907-1971
  - Correspondence, 1940-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Minutes books, 1930-1940 (Box-folder 1-2-4)
  - Minutes, 1940-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5-7)
  - Programs, 1934-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 1-8-9)
  - Newsletters and circular letters, 1955-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Annual reports, 1954-1970 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Bank statements, 1949-1971 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Budgets, 1954-1969 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Checks, 1949-1971 (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Dues receipt books, 1953-1970 (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Financial documents, 1941-1971 (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1940-1971 (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Account / membership roster books, 1940-1971 (Box-folder 2-9-10)
  - Membership rosters, 1940-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 2-11)
  - History, constitution, and bylaws, 1954, n.d. (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Awards, 1959-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Yearbooks, 1932-1947 (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Yearbooks, 1948-1970 (Box-folder 3-1-4)
  - Summer music camps, 1961-1969, n.d. (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Scrapbooks, 1935-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 3-6-11)
  - Scrapbooks, 1956-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 4-1-8)
  - Photographs, newspaper clippings, and ephemera, 1940-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 4-9)
  - Music Club Programs from All Nations, 1907 (Box-folder 4-10)
  - Other organizations, 1940-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 5-1)
- Series II. Virginia Federation of Music Clubs, 1933-1971
  - District I, 1933-1969,n.d. (Box-folder 5-2)
  - Circular letters, 1945-1969,n.d. (Box-folder 5-3)
  - Administrative and promotional materials, 1947-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 5-4)
  - Annual conventions, 1936-1969 (Box-folder 5-5)
  - History, constitution, and bylaws, 1947-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 5-6)
  - Directories, 1961-1970 (Box-folder 5-7)
  - Virginia Musician, 1962 (Box-folder 5-8)
- Series III. National Federation of Music Clubs, 1944-1971
  - Reports to convention, 1963 (Box-folder 5-9)
  - Circular letters, 1959-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 5-10)
  - Announcements and other communications, 1959-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 5-11)
  - Price lists and order forms, 1960-1969, n.d. (Box-folder 5-12)
  - Printed material, 1944-1971, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 5-13)